<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Introspective | Tacks.io < Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://tacksapp.github.io/blog/categories/introspective/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tacksapp.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-21T16:02:29+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://tacksapp.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ian Dundas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Looking Back for Inspiration Part 1: Gigsniffr]]></title>
    <link href="http://tacksapp.github.io/blog/2014/04/21/looking-back-for-inspiration-part1/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-21T15:30:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://tacksapp.github.io/blog/2014/04/21/looking-back-for-inspiration-part1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Perhaps my fondest memory in all my time spent coding was the all-out dash to build a complex PHP web-app for my undergrad dissertation. It was the biggest project I&rsquo;d ever attempted, and was the starting-gun I&rsquo;d been waiting for, the opportunity to really dig into something.</p>

<p>Man, I was so psyched about my idea &ndash; it was a web-scraper named Gigsniffr which aggregated a set of concert ticket websites. The killer feature was that when it saw a ticket come onsale for a user&rsquo;s favourite band, it alerted them via a tweet (back when Twitter was still conceived of as a computer-human API platform). At the time, nothing much like this yet existed (2007 was also when <a href="http://songkick.com/">Songkick</a> launched), and I knew for sure that it could be big if I could <em>just</em> get it launched.</p>

<p>This was before any of these music sites had a published API for me to use, so I had to really research how to put together a reliable web-scraping algorithm that could repeatedly spider the ticket sites.</p>

<p>The project was incredibly fun: I was developing into (for me) the complete unknown &ndash; I wasn&rsquo;t amazing at PHP, I had no experience of managing a long-running web-scraper service, I had no permission to scrape these sites, I had a hard deadline to hit, and nothing to distract me.</p>

<p>There were many problems to solve: how can you work out the names of a user&rsquo;s nearest cities, without Google&rsquo;s Map API; how do you build an engine to accurately scrape many different websites, abstracting away from the quirks of each (answer: invent own XPath tricks); how do you diff the data collected with that taken an hour previously?</p>

<p>I soon found that the first pass of data gathering was easy &ndash;  but updating and correcting this dataset was actually much harder: I was attempting to keep track of gig cancellations, date changes, and variances in band names (Red Hot Chili Peppers vs RHCP etc), and it was a rathole without end. Much fun to solve!</p>

<p>I did manage to get a prototype working in time for the deadline &ndash; an achievement which to this day I&rsquo;m proud of. At the presentation were two local entrepreneurs who took an interest in my idea and took me out for lunch to discuss it.</p>

<p>Alas &ndash; I ground to a halt somewhere between finishing the proof-of-concept and launching a user-ready product.  After I&rsquo;d delivered the proof-of-concept and completed the course, the pressure was off and it was time to relax &ndash; I&rsquo;d hit the deadline and could now continue developing Gigsniffr at my leisure, right after I&rsquo;ve been to these music festivals and learned Ruby and started a job and&hellip;</p>

<p>.. and it was gradually forgotten. The would-be investors were interested only in funding marketing, and only once the app was finished &ndash; they were not interested in financing even the peanuts I&rsquo;d need to sit down and complete it. I was also messed up after a nasty breakup. I found myself in a job that absorbed 10 hours of coding stamina per day, which I then quit to take a Masters &ndash; without any real gap after the undergrad. If I&rsquo;m honest, I&rsquo;d got what I wanted from the project, and was moving on &ndash; so Gigsniffr was shelved.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve a profound admiration for those running startups which actually launch, especially those who succeed longterm &ndash; it&rsquo;s an amazing feat. People say that ideas are cheap, and that building them is the hard bit. What they don&rsquo;t mention is that building the interesting parts of a project is pretty easy, but FINISHING it is nearly impossible in comparison. Finishing a product really is hard. But the burst of real energy and creativity I summoned for Gigsniffr is something I&rsquo;ve been chasing ever since.</p>

<p><em>Prototype Homepage</em></p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://i.imgur.com/RG6aM7Gl.png">http://i.imgur.com/RG6aM7Gl.png</a>" title="Landing Page" ></p>

<p><em>Prototype Admin panel</em></p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://i.imgur.com/ogIVXZB.png">http://i.imgur.com/ogIVXZB.png</a>" title="Admin panel" ></p>

<p><em>Prototype scraping control panel</em></p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://i.imgur.com/iNIPvgFl.png">http://i.imgur.com/iNIPvgFl.png</a>" title="Scraping admin panel" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
